it is my pleasure to introduce Trey
Granger who is going to say things that
are probably much better planned than
what I've been
saying all right I think we're good
we'll go with it all right good morning
everybody um I am here today to talk
about personalizing search using
multimodal Laten behavioral embeddings
um you can s shorten that to just
personalized search um it's a little bit
of a um uh I don't know what the right
terminology is but it's it's an area of
search that everybody kind of knows
about but that um doesn't get a lot of
attention U because it's weird um yeah
we know about uh running keyword search
lexical search we know about uh dense
Vector search with embeddings and and
semantic search and all these different
topics um um some are more um invogue
right now but personalized search I
think is a very interesting area uh of
information retrieval and I just want to
talk a little bit about it today some
techniques for implementing it and then
um hopefully at the end we should have
some time for questions and some general
discussion around it but I want to share
some techniques that you guys might find
interesting uh as you're implementing
whether it's a rag system whether it's a
traditional you know keyword-based
system semantic you know Vector based
system what have you so uh off we go um
a little bit about me I am the the uh uh
founder of search kernel which is a uh
you know AI powered search consulting
company um also the lead author on the
AI power search book I'll talk a little
bit more about that uh with Doug who
presented yesterday I think everybody
knows Doug uh formerly I was the CTO at
pre-search which is a decentralized web
search engine um and before that I was
the chief algorithms officer at Lucid
works and before that the SVP of
engineering at Lucid works and before
that I was at CareerBuilder
uh the AI power search book um quick
plug for it um it's coming out in about
two months um it is finished um we're
just we're going through the production
process with Manning right now um two
other plugs for everybody here uh given
the um level of intellectual Capital we
have at this conference related to
search and information retrieval um uh
one uh we have reworked the book in
recent months uh to make it search
engine agnostic what I mean by that is
it can't work with you know any database
but uh for most of the major vendors the
ones at this conference um you know the
book was originally written to use
Apache solar um it still uses solar by
default but all of the examples work um
in an sort of slightly abstracted way
away from the core engine so if any uh
and and we've got an appendix at the
back of the book for supported search
engines and Vector databases so um if
anyone who I have not already spoken to
um is interested in potentially
integrating with the book so that the
book will work with your technology and
you can you know use the book to promote
your technology Etc definitely reach out
to me either at the conference or or
afterwards so just a quick plug there uh
also as we get ready to launch the book
um I know many of you have read it many
of you have Early Access copies um if
you're interested in you know providing
a quote about your thoughts on the book
hopefully positive or review or you know
anything like that in terms of helping
us promote it I would definitely love to
chat with you as well um that'
definitely be greatly appreciated uh the
book covers topics from retrieval
augmented generation generative search
and summarization learning to rank
semantic search D Vector search find
tuning LMS and search automated learning
to rank going all the way from you know
building a learning to rank model by
hand using manual judgments to
generating automated judgments from uh
in Click models from implicit user
feedback and signals uh to Active
Learning and you know exploration of of
other things it includes um sort of what
you would expect in terms of you know uh
the latest in terms of uh leveraging
Transformers and llms and do multimodal
search and those kinds of things uh it
also includes typical reflected
intelligence type approaches like
signals boosting um you know uh
recommendations and collaborative
filtering and the personaliz search I'm
going to talk stuff I'm going to talk
about today um it's not designed to be a
latest and greatest model type book it's
designed to be the uh sort of design
patterns for implementing search and a
data driven machine machine learning
based way so it's it's not it's not
going to be an evergreen book cuz our
space is changing incredibly fast but
hopefully for years to come it will be
sort of best practices for in to end
implementing uh AI powered search so
quick plug there's a discount code um
get it if you're interested and off we
go to personalize search uh so the
agenda for today I'm going to talk a
little bit about the personalization
spectrum between search and
recommendations uh how to leverage user
signals their behaviors and interactions
to implement collaborative filtering and
personalization um from latent features
uh use embedding vectors to generate
personalization profiles of users um mix
user signals and content based
attributes to generate multimodal
personalization uh clustering products
that uh by embeddings to create uh
personalization guardrails uh uh context
basically for the personalization and
then finally avoiding some of the
pitfalls of personaliz
search um so before we get into all of
that I want to start with a A this seems
like kind of a dumb question but it's
actually a really hard question Believe
It or Not My question is what is an
embedding and this isn't this is for
actual I want some audience
participation here so who thinks they've
got a good definition of what an
embedding
is oh so go
ahead dat a numerical representation of
one or more pieces of data so like 12
maybe
okay Audrey yeah did you you have
something uh I was G to
say I guess a
represent an AI representation of data
thatat okay let me get one more Yep
similarly a vector
representation of a series of features
that you can compare distance angle
between that represented in space so you
can see how far apart there interesting
okay so um we all could look at an
embedding and say hey that's an
embedding right so we we talk about
embed embeddings or um I like the
terminology thought vectors though that
doesn't seem to have caught on um you
know we've got like word and phrase
embeddings sentence
embeddings uh paragraph embeddings
document embed ings um and so what I
figured I would do is go to the experts
in terms of you know what what does the
word embedding mean and by the experts I
mean what results come up on the first
page of you know Google or duck. go
search results and then from those
filter out random blog posts and focus
on like companies that should be able to
Define this right so I picked a few
examples um one's from hugging face that
they seem like they would be legit right
um their definition of an embedding is a
numerical representation of a piece of
information
pretty good um Cloud flare I don't know
why they show up at the top but they
help that I think they have I don't know
for whatever reason um embeddings are
vectors created by Machine learning
models for the purpose of capturing
meaningful data about each object so by
their definition if I make my own
embedding if I put a vector together of
features that's not an embedding I guess
because it wasn't created by a machine
learning model um hugging faces if it's
not a numeric representation it's not an
embedding well that's interesting we'll
come back to that uh Google there's is
very confusing this is from a training
course they have an embedding is a
relatively low-dimensional space into
which you can translate high-dimensional
vectors I included extra context because
that was very confusing to me embeddings
make it easier to do machine learning in
large inputs like sparse vectors
representing words good ideally and
embedding captures some of the semantics
of the input by placing semantically
similar inputs together in the embedding
space so I think they actually defined
embedding as embedding space but either
way it's the whole thing is confusing
IBM embedding is a means of representing
objects like text images and audio as
points in a continuous Vector space
where the locations of those points in
space are semantically meaningful so
that's probably the best of the ones
here I would say I've still got a few
little issues with it but we'll get to
those but I'm going to give my own
definition of embedding that is a little
bit more abstracted than
these an embedding is a coordinate and a
vector space into which we map a
concept um and why I'm being so careful
and precise here um if you think about
where the where the phrase embedding
came from um I uh it's not my favorite
word I again thought Vector something
like that I prefer but the idea of an
embedding is that you actually are
taking a concept and you're taking a
vector space and you're sticking that
Concept in the vector space somewhere
and so if you this is easy easy to
visualize with you know images right if
you go to like the the gomic um example
here where you can search for Darth
Vader and then these particular images
are these coordinates in this Vector
space uh the vector space has been
defined and you're saying here's my
vector and the vector is the set of
coordinates that get you to the place in
Vector space that represents the concept
you're talking about and so I'm going to
go with
this definition for this talk um and I
think it also opens up room for some
other things that we'll talk about later
but it's a coordinate in a vector space
I didn't say in a numerical continuous
float Vector space I just said it's a
coordinate in a vector space into which
we map a concept all right so we'll
continue on so these are all just
different things you find in a vector
space some puppies here um always makes
talks better when you have cute puppies
um all right so taking that a little a
step further I would argue that an
inverted index creates embeddings which
have one dimension per term so if you
think of you know hey if I if every
single keyword or term in my index is a
feature is a dimension maybe there's
millions of them um and if it exists
there's a one and if it doesn't it's a
zero I would call that an embedding it's
not a semantically meaningful embedding
beyond that individual word because I'm
the coordinate I'm giving is still in a
vector space right it's it's really in
the same Vector space that we would map
you know any kind of language into and
concept into it's just that it's
represented by millions of features Each
of which have a single term versus you
know being condensed down into 1,24 512
or what have you
features uh embedding map Concepts into
another Vector space usually a lower
dimensional space so I can take all the
words of my inverted index all the words
of my Corpus I can then map them down
into 1,024 dimensions and those can be
latent features in some um embedding
model um I would also argue that you
could take features and you could expand
them to more Dimensions you don't have
to always do dimensionality reduction
the value of dimensionality reduction is
that we can uh go from a higher level
like like a bunch of keywords for
example and when we compress them down
into lower Dimensions we uh unveil some
connections some semantically meaningful
connections between
the items that were previously at a
higher dimensionality but I would argue
we could also extend the dimensionality
we do this if you think of like you know
uh sparse um Vector search you think
things like Spade what do we do we take
a word we find other things and we
expand out and and the the features
we're searching for we're actually
expanding because we we we can you could
argue it's the same Vector space maybe
but either way the the embedding got
expanded and and represents more meaning
now and of course we um you know take
these embeddings we um leverage them in
the vector space to explore similarity
so if I've got these um embeddings over
here on the left for apple juice
cappuccino a bunch of food items I do my
cosign similarity do product Idan does
whatever distance um I I then I'm
exploring the relationships based upon
those shared features between things
this is the basic basis for um all the
the dense Vector search um and and all
the llm capabilities we're exploring
these days
but with llms and other Foundation
models the dimensions learned are latent
features so on the last slide when I was
showing you know cappuccino and showing
a bunch of terms I manually defined some
categories that were the features and so
they they were just you know they
weren't latent they were just things I
defined but when we use neural networks
to train uh uh Transformers and and and
embedding models we at that point are
you know what all the features represent
is not like one thing right it's a
combination of all the features together
and those combinations um basically
unveil latent features that describe uh
the documents and we're going to return
to this later because I'm going to get
off of embeddings for a second but this
is going to be really important when we
start to think about how we handle
signals and use those in a sort of you
know a vectorized embedding sort of way
um so this is a slide I have in
basically every presentation I ever give
um it's the dimensions of user content
and uh the point of this slide is that
our job as information retrieval
Specialists is to help users find what
they're looking for might be a document
might be an answer might be an action
might be uh you know a task of going and
doing something but either way the user
wants something and our job is to help
them find it in order to do that we need
to understand three contexts you know as
best as possible one of them is the
content that we have that we're
searching over another is the user what
is their context what do they care about
and the third is the domain you know the
user might say a word that doesn't have
any meaning in the domain but the user
thinks it means something so we need
understand the user there there's domain
specific terminology we need to
understand and then there's you know the
content that we actually have and so if
you take just content understanding
you're talking about something like
keyword search if you take just domain
understanding you're talking about a
Knowledge Graph now that could be an llm
that could be an explicit Knowledge
Graph a semantic knowledge graph but the
idea is it's something that understands
the your domain the terminology and and
and what um how the concepts relate and
then of course if it's pure user
understanding I don't have any content I
don't know anything about the domain I'm
just looking at user behavior and trying
to you know match and rank based upon
that that's like collaborative filtering
that's collaborative recommendations
purely based upon behavior when you look
at the intersections between these
things the intersection between content
understanding user understanding is
personalized search which we'll talk
about today intersection between keyword
search and knowledge graphs is semantic
search uh and then I'm not going to get
the other one because it's boring but um
user intent is the intersection of all
of these and so what we're going to talk
about today is that personalized search
part the the intersection at the very
top all of these topics are interesting
there's lots of i' I've given lots of
presentations there's coverage of all of
it in the book but uh today is about
personalize search so the
personalization Spectrum uh spans uh I
used to call this the information
retrieval Spectrum but it's to
generalize so the personalization
Spectrum goes everywhere from
traditional keyword search all the way
to traditional or collaborative
recommendations at a lot of
organizations you've got you know your
search team and they focus on user input
and keywords you've got your
recommendations team and they focus on
matching based upon user profiles but
it's all the same thing at the end of
the day we're taking
context and we're using that context to
match content or um documents or or what
have you so in the context of
traditional keyword search the context
we have to do matching is what the user
types in they type in some keywords they
specify some filters that is our only
context for traditional recommendations
our only context is uh you know
information about the user their profile
but we're not taking anything from them
explicitly but of course there's this
massive area in between for personalized
queries which are mostly specified by
the user they're typing things in but we
use what we know about the user to
augment what we show them and of course
user guided recommendations where you're
given recommendations but you can say oh
actually don't use this item to
influence my recommendations and can you
filter my recommendations by this
category they're both search and
recommendations this is sort of a hybrid
model but the point is um user context
is part of the intent that we need to
understand when we're matching for
search um if we dig a little bit deeper
into that Spectrum I I basically just
took the last two slides and overlaid
them on top of each other um we've got
the intersection of uh keyword search um
and uh uh user driven Behavior
collaborative recomendations and in
between we have those personalized
queries and user guided recommendations
um and I'll talk about recommendations
first and then we'll come back to the
personalized queries so um
recommendation approaches you guys are
probably all familiar with
recommendations I'm not going to go in
detail but we've got um content based
matching which we often do in search
engines right you know here's some
information I know about the the user
let me match uh you know whatever this
user type detergent and I know that
fabric software are detergent and dryer
sheets are all related because they have
similar you know terms or categories or
clustering or what have you so you can
do recommendations based purely on
content you can do behavior-based or
collaborative recommendations using
collaborative filtering algorithms which
we'll talk about today um and then you
can of course do hybrid um matching
hybrid recommendations using both
content-based filtering and
collaborative filtering and combin in
them together um most recommendation
systems do this because it works way
better than one or the other it helps
you overcome the cold start problem um
and it leverages your user Behavior as
best as possible um but another sort of
audience question section so um for
collaborative filtering I want you to
look at this for a second so
collaborative filtering doesn't know
anything about your content it's got
documents basically and that's it um but
I want you guys to look at just the
titles here knowing what these documents
are I want you to tell me
what's similar about these
users anyone can raise their
hand
yep movies characters they're all movies
Okay
yepy they're all owned by Disney um The
Dark Knight and the Batman are not for
and yeah but most of them are maybe some
of the users are similar and others are
maybe there's clusters of them like what
do you guys see any obvious clusters
amongst users super us
and
Disney what's classic
Disney the kids cartoons the cartoons
okay the kids okay so the the user
forign five like cartoon Disney cartoons
it looks like uh users one two and three
like
superheroes um three likes some non-
Disney superheroes everybody else likes
Disney superheroes but yeah you guys you
can look at this and E even if you
didn't know the titles of the movies you
know that the people who would watch
these even if you just had IDs here
these clusters would would would be
found even with no content right um so
yeah there that's what that's how
collaborative filtering Works sort of
intuitively um this is we're not going
to go through code here but this is an
implementation of one collaborative
filtering algorithm called ALS or
alternatingly squares um it basically
well I'll get into how it works um
shortly but um when you run this uh for
a user so I've got this user here um
this is somebody who previously ran two
searches one for apple and one for
MacBook and then they clicked
on the Apple iPad 2 the they added that
to the C to their shopping cart they
purchased it and then they also clicked
on an Apple MacBook Air so that is the
context we have about that user based
upon that context and just doing
collaborative filtering if we take those
results we you know get the idas of the
things they've interacted with or we do
collaborative filtering and then we sort
of boost documents in our search engine
that are related to the things they've
interacted with then we get something
like this on the right where it's a
bunch of you know apple and tablet
boosted types things type of things this
is being done as a search query in my
search engine so this can be this can
augment a user search if they type
something you can boost things up that
are similar to what they've done before
this is one way of doing personalization
of search results very common way
um and so like just as an example if I
just search when search for tablet and
this naive out of thebox you know bline
based search engine um it's doing bm25
on my keyword of tablet these are the
results I get how do you guys feel about
those
results the bm25 score is
great they're not good right they don't
have domain context they don't have user
context uh when I add in the boosting
based upon um the items the users
interacted with before and the
recommendations for those then the
results get much better so that's one
way of doing personalized search uh
another way of doing personalized search
is using embeddings so if we go back to
this notion of an embedding having
latent features so these are these are
features associated with these items at
the top so you've got you know a two
tablets of different colors uh looks
like a two washing machines maybe a
phone and a phone a phone screen or
screen cover for a phone um and so
there's a whole bunch of features in the
vector um these are latent features
meaning they don't represent any one
particular thing but the combination of
them does and and some numbers being
higher are leaning towards certain items
so for example this top one seems like
it has something to do with size or at
least it's implicated in size because
the bigger these things are the bigger
this number seems to be you know color
is implicated here you know the darker
it is it looks like it's got a higher
score the lighter it is looks like it
has a lower score this embedding kind of
means something like it's computer like
um it's it's a it's some concept of you
know technology is computer is the last
one seems to have something to do with
the the price um again they're not
explicit features but they're latent
features Um this can be extracted from
content going back to ALS and to our
collaborative recommendations the way
that ALS actually works is that it it
you create a user item interaction
Matrix um so you basically take all the
users you take all the items they've
interacted with the white squares here
are items they haven't interacted with
so it's just we don't know if they would
like this or not uh for for ALS when you
implement it it uses Matrix
factorization which essentially tries to
take that that user item interaction
Matrix and convert it into two other
matrices one is a user feature Matrix
and the other is an item feature Matrix
normally when we're implementing
collaborative filtering we generate that
and then we use that to and we multiply
it back to generate something that
approximates the original Matrix and
that's how we do our recommendations so
that's how we recommend things the users
never seen before but this intermediate
form here is very interesting in the
context of personalization because what
we've just done is we've
generated latent features that describe
users and latent features that describe
items just like our embeddings coming
from content that have latent features
that describe content we now have more
latent features that describe content
but these features didn't come from the
content they describes items these
features came from interactions with the
items meaning in addition to the uh the
embeddings that we can learn from just
analyzing the entire web and you know
building a giant large language model we
can also analyze our users information
to probably find very highly overlapping
latent features but also maybe discover
latent features that don't exist in the
content that the LM we're trained from
even if it's our own data that
fine-tuned the llms because the users
have Insight that aren't isn't
necessarily in the data so these latent
features we can take and use as
embeddings and use them to help you know
match uh content so come back to that in
a bit but um learned embeddings of users
allow us to personalize results whether
it's you know just from their actions
and we use those to map to vectors that
are content based or whether we um you
know derive the embeddings from the
user's behaviors um and so these are two
examples of personalized search and I'll
show you the code for these momentarily
um the one on the left um has what has
no personalization guard rails and I
need to Define what that means but think
of it as when I'm doing
personalization um this user has
previously searched for and maybe
clicked on a Hello Kitty plush toy
they've searched for a GE electric razor
that's in Black they've searched for a
GE bright white light bulb and they've
searched for a Samsung stainless
refrigerator all of those things are
things the user has interacted with
naively if we try to implement some sort
of uh personalization based upon those
items you're going to get something like
this on the left so they search for
microwave you're going to get a black
microwave because they search for black
razor you're going to get a Hello Kitty
microwave because apparently that exists
um and they apparently like Hello Kitty
and you're going to get this white
microwave from GE because they search
for GE electric razor and GE white light
bulbs so um even though what they pre
which of these items is the most
relevant for what they're looking for
right now would you say out of these
four up
here Samsung stainless steel
refrigerator all of you knew that that
was the most relevant how do you know
that it's an appliance right you've got
the context that oh this is an appliance
I should probably look at their
preferences within the context of
Appliance so let's Implement that and
get what we have here on the right
instead um so one one way of doing that
that is we can take all of our items um
we might have category labels already
assigned to them I actually do in this
data set but let's throw that out we're
just going to Cluster all of our items
so that we can generate Dynamic
categories for the items um also
categories that have similarities and
are close to each other in a vector
space so that we're not creating hard um
delineations so I'm not going to go
through the code you guys can look at
the code afterwards but um this is code
to um to Cluster products based upon
embedding so the specific these are um
embeddings generated from the content of
the product so this is you know titles
descriptions that kind of thing based
upon that we map all of our products
into a vector space uh and then we
cluster um based upon those to generate
these clusters here so you know we've
got many more Dimensions than this but
if we you know uh do dimensionality
reduction down to you know two
Dimensions here you can see that all of
my products sort of fall into the space
and it might be a you guys in in here
can see it um on Zoom hopefully you can
as well but what what you see is that up
at the top right here you have things
that are CDs mostly music CDs having to
do with music um over here on the left
I've got ranges microwaves stainless
steel range self cleaning so this seems
to be appliances over here down at the
bottom right I've got widescreen DVD DVD
widescreen this this seems to be video
sort of content so so audio is at the
top video is down here so whatever this
Dimension is you know sound things and
video is things down here um you know
Appliance is things versus you know CDs
and digital medish things over here um
you see like computer memory these kinds
of things down here but you get the idea
we've taken all of our products and
we've clustered them and these are the
Clusters the the centers of the Clusters
and I've given them all labels now that
I have
that we've got our products mapped into
clusters why don't I map my queries into
clusters as well so the user comes in
and we're going to use the same search
they're searching for microwave so um
and again the codes here I'm not going
to go through the code you guys can look
at that later but I'm just going to talk
about the ideas what we're essentially
doing is taking the query and mapping it
into the Clusters that we've generated
for the content to generate these
contexts into which we person under
which we personalize um and there's a
kind of three different ways of doing
that there's more but you know three
obvious ways of doing that one is we do
a k means on you know hey we've got our
clusters let's find you know whichever
cluster is going to be the closest based
upon our space another ways to do a
cosine predicted cluster so hey I've got
a vector for my query I've got a vector
for my all my documents let me do a
cosine and find the Clusters that are
the most that are the closest um then
the last one which is what I recommend
is we do we use the cosine but we get
multiple clusters so I don't want to if
I've got a category you may have seen it
on the last slide where I've got here's
my ranges and here's my stoves and
here's my refrigerators and here's my
freezers they're they're all appliances
they're all kind of similar so you don't
want to hard cut somebody off to be in
just one of the things that where where
the product happened to get clustered so
instead if we say hey just find me the
five closest clusters and I'm going to
use that context to um to to limit my
personalization um so that's what we're
doing here so I'm finding the five
closest clusters within our products to
microwave and so you see here it's you
know microwave stainless steel oven
stainless steel black kitchena you know
30-in range stainless steel range
refrigerator all appliances um and just
for reference these labels just came
from finding the top keywords in each
cluster so that's where the labels came
from just so you know kind of what
you're looking at um and then we're
going to use those so once we have those
we've got a couple of different
approaches we can use to take those
contexts and the user's query um and map
them into an embedding based personal
ation I'm using an embedding for the
user one is we could perform a weight
and sorry this is a lot of text so just
you can look at the yellow or just
listen uh we perform a weighted average
between the query Vector um so the
embedding for microwave and the vectors
for the user's previous interactions
with the predicted cluster so that would
generate a single Vector representing a
personalized version of the user's query
so all the results would be personalized
um we probably don't we may or may not
want to do that another way is to
perform a standard search but then you
know keyword or vector um or hybrid or
what have you and then boost the results
based on the average of the embeddings
from a user's previous interactions with
the predicted cluster uh that would be a
hybrid keyword in Vector based ranking
function where the keyword search would
be the primary driver of the results but
the user's previous interactions would
be um to would be used to boost related
results higher um third option do either
one of the above but then only
personalize a few items and the search
results so instead of you know my tin
results being all personalized I might
say hey let me maybe leave result one
and two and boost like maybe just
sprinkle some personalization in in case
we're wrong or in case the user doesn't
like personalization so most of the
results look good this is often a good
approach it's a very conservative
approach and you know not a bad one for
many use cases um and then the last
option here is to perform a standard
search again keyword or vector or hybrid
uh and then rerank the results based on
the weighted average between the query
vector and the vectors for the users's
previous interactions with the predicted
clusters so you saw that I got multiple
clusters coming back some of them maybe
weight higher than others but I if I
sort of take a a weighted average um
between the query vector and the the
vectors for the user's previous
interactions then I can use that as my
personalization Vector for the user so
um again I don't want to spend time on
code because we'll do hopefully
questions and stuff at the end but um
this is code to generated a
personalization Vector um for the user
um see if there's anything here get
personalization Vector we're calling in
code on a
Transformer um C embeddings wait taking
average uh so it's just a vector that
combines the weighted average embedding
for the query uh yeah I'm going to keep
moving on for this one look at the code
later um once we've done that we can
generate contextual um uh embeddings uh
contextual user personalization vectors
so um on the left here I'm taking these
are the items that the users interacted
with before so this top item is a Hello
Kitty water bottle and this next one is
a uh stainless seel electric range for
reference and we're um getting the user
embedding taking the query microwave uh
this unfiltered personalization Vector
is getting a vector that just uses all
of those embeddings to you know boost
the search results this filtered one is
getting the context um of you know what
uh uh clusters have been interacted with
before so over here on the right you can
see um these are the product
interactions for the user these two
items the Hello Kitty water bottle and
the stainless steel electric range um
with no cluster guard rails no context
being added this is my you know average
Vector of their past interactions if I
use that to boost the results um you'll
see the Hello Kitty microwave show up
that example from earlier but if I find
the Clusters that they've interacted
with or sorry I find the cluster for the
query and then I filter the past
behaviors that I'm going to use for
personalization based upon the Clusters
that are related to the query now I'm
taking maybe they've maybe the user has
interacted with a 100 things but I'm
going to filter it down to only the five
things that are in this category or
cluster of categories um and and then
I'm only personalization personalizing
in this case for appliances and so now
I'm basically only using that one
embedding or sorry I'm only using that
one item because the other ones got
filtered out because they're not related
to um appliances and so this ends up
being my personalization V for the for
the user with the guard rails
um this codee's boring this just runs
different scenarios the first one is uh
just a basic search with no
personalization um uh the second one is
uh oh sorry yeah the second one is um uh
doing Global personalization and then
the third one it generates is uh
contextual personalization with the CATE
with the Clusters this is what the
results look like so this is just a
search for microwave you know I see a
white microwave
a stainless steal microwave a microwave
popper for popcorn and the Hello Kitty
microwave down here so that's no
personalization that's what you would
get out of the box uh with global
personalization that beautiful Hello
Kitty microwave is here um and a bunch
of other random microwaves and then with
my contextual personalization for only
you know considering categories that are
related to what the user is currently
searching for I get a bunch of stainless
steel microwaves you know way better
than the other
approaches um last thing I want to kind
of mention here uh is we we're talking
about the um the uh latent features that
you can derive from user signals by
doing Matrix factorization um and we
think about multimodal models often oh
yeah text to video text and image to VI
like all of these different me
modalities uh the reality is uh yeah
we've got text we've got images but user
behavior is one modality that that I
think is highly unexplored currently
within our space um the reasons are
pretty obvious you know hey we had
keyword searched and we got Vector
search these llms are amazing we get
these embeddings for free other people
pay millions or tens of million tens of
millions of dollars to train them for us
and it just kind of is Magic we just put
the embeddings in there and it's all
just magic right but we're ignoring our
user context we're ignoring our data
that can tell us more information so
it's definitely
possible uh to do know joint um
uh joint encoding embedding models to to
sort of factor in these additional
features that come from user behavior um
I would highly recommend I think that we
explore those areas um also you know my
general context in the book the context
as well is that there's many different
query modalities so I there's a lot of
talk here about hybrid search right and
I think when people say hybrid search
usually what they mean is lexical
and D Spector I'm going to call it
semantic semantic means a lot but um
they mean oh let's combine these two
different things together my view is
it's not two things my view is there's a
lot of things right there's you know
like what do you do in a traditional
query pipeline well you parse the
query of course you get keywords
locations things like that you do a
signals boosting model to try to make
sure that your most popular results get
boost at the top a popularized relevance
algorithm you do you know sort of
knowledge graph look UPS now this can be
llm based or this can be semantic
Knowledge Graph or what have you but you
you look up things that are related to
your query to add some structure and
understanding to it you um you know
maybe do lexical search on inverted
index you know filtering on categories
you do uh you know sparse Vector
expansion with things like Spade or
semantic knowledge graphs U maybe apply
Geo filters you know things like that
that you don't get with the dense I mean
like certain models have certain
capabilities but these are all different
um modalities for hybrid right like
these are all hybrid type queries that
you put together Additionally you know
the DSE Vector self with cosine similar
to dot product or Hamming distance or
what have you um you know we've got back
filling you might do personalization
recommendations and but all of those
things together in a pipeline or maybe
multiple pipelines depending on the
context are ways of doing information
retrieval they're ways of matching and
ranking and to me hybrid means take all
of these different techniques take you
know signals boosting collaborative
filtering learning to rank dense Vector
sparse Vector query expansion sparse
query expansion um you know take click
model like take all of it and use the
appropriate tool where you need it um so
it's it's to me it's
not hybrid you know keyword lexical
versus dense it's it's hey there's a lot
of techniques we use here in AI powered
search and we need to combine them all
together um last thing on just signals
so the idea this idea of reflective
intelligence or feedback loops is really
important in AI powered search so we
talked about collaborative filtering and
taking user Behavior building models we
feed that back into the system so the
personalization is constantly getting
better the recommendations are
constantly getting better um but there's
lots of different uh AI power search
algorithms that we use for things like
this so you know whether it's signals
boosting uh feedback loops uh
collaborative filtering based reflected
intelligence learning to rank based
where you're getting implicit judgments
from user signals and click models or
these sort of personalization profiles
like we looked at today um I would just
encourage you guys to you know think
about these things and try to get them
implemented where they make sense within
your uh products and customers so that's
it for me uh AI power search is the book
check it out um talk with me if you're
interested in you know integrating or
helping to promote it and uh I don't
know if I've got any time for questions
one or two okay thanks
guys thank you Trey we have time for a
question or two
to I see a hand so close yeah you're
welcome thank you um I know some of this
some of the text look like it was
plagiarized on a book that I read called
AI powered search don't don't tell the
author yeah but um uh you're you're
basic like and you know summed up that
we should be doing all of these things
um H is do you have guidance on how to
combine these like I'm I'm
ah yeah real questions please real
questions next thank you for the great
talk uh you mentioned personalization
and user interactions to me that
something we can do with historical data
but also with firsttime visitors what do
you think about a realtime
personalization of anonymous visitors
sure got um so real time person of
anonymous visitors so um I think of
search as taking context and using it to
match and rank so whether that's
keywords whether that's user what you
know about the user so say someone comes
to your I'm going to let's say it's a
job search website someone comes to it
for the first time what context do you
have about them you know their location
from their IP address right so if they
come to your homepage and you're showing
some jobs should you show them jobs in
Japan and London and South Africa no you
should show them jobs where they're
located that is personalization that is
first time all the contacts I have about
you is your location and so I'm going to
use it if someone likewise comes to the
site and they type in Atlanta Georgia
but you know that they're registered
nurse should you be showing them
software engineering jobs and you know
brain surgeon jobs like no you should be
you should you you might show them the
same set of results but you're going to
boost results that are more likely to be
relevant for them at the top those are
light ways of doing personalization that
almost always make sense and don't
frustrate users
um as you continue to get more
interactions you get more context
obviously you have to be careful like we
did with the guard rails and make sure
you're not um over applying
personalization because you can really
frustrate people if you personalize
something they're not expecting it you
have to apply it with a light touch but
um but yeah absolutely you should use
whatever context you have you should
take whatever context you have use
whatever means you have to figure out if
you should use that context in your
query and then use it if it makes
sense yeah all right we have time for
just one more from the zoom Alexandra
asks how do you measure
personalization how do you measure
personalization I assume you mean in ter
so I'm going to assume that he means in
terms of um uh like Precision recall the
typical IR metrics okay so I'll just I
I'll go with go with it um at the end of
the day our job is to give the user what
they're looking for to meet their intent
um we have metrics for standard keyword
search where we've had people create
judgments and we measure those it's it's
very hard to do that with
personalization because every result set
changes for every user um so what you
typically would do is tie it to a
business metric so like if it's product
search you tie it to hey are we selling
more is like you maybe look at um uh
drop off rate things like that um um you
know you could also just see about user
satisfaction but I I think that um it is
harder to measure because you can't have
a standard training set that you use to
um to to measure it based upon so you
have to look at I think some other
metrics that are about overall business
success and overall success of the
engine it helping the user meet their
need versus just you know something more
static thank you Trey and let's thank
our speaker all right thanks everybody
appreciate it we have 12 minutes until
the next
talk e